<?xml version = '1.0' encoding = 'UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
  <header>
    <title>Skolt Sami Rule File</title>
    <authors>
      <person email="trond.trosterud@hum.uit.no" name="Trond Trosterud" />
    </authors>
  </header>
  <body>
    <section>
      <title>Documenting the Skolt Sami Rule file</title>
      <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <section>
          <title>xfst vs. twolc</title>
          <p>The Skolt Sami rule file differs from the other languages in being an xfst file, rather than a twolc file (each format have different chapters in the pdf version of the Xerox book). The differences between thesew two formats may be summarised as follows:</p>
          <ul>
            <li>xfst rules are ordered, whereas twolc rules apply simultaneously</li>
            <li>xfst rules stand in a feeding-bleeding relation to each other, whereas twolc rules do not</li>
            <li>xfst rules are good at doing many-to-many replacement operations (also of different-size strings), whereas in twolc one must have one rule for each pair of members in equal-length strings</li>
            <li>xfst cannot generalise over ordered sets of pairs, thus the Cx:Cy replacement of members of ordered sets Cx and Cy that is found in twolc must be done in a more clumsy way in xfst.</li>
          </ul>
          <p>The reason why xfst is chosen for Skolt Sami (and in the future also for Inari Sami(?)) is that there are several cases of many-to-many replacements in the Skolt Sami grammar.</p>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>The structure of the rule file itself</title>
          <p>The rule file for Skolt Sami is divided into 5 main types:</p>
          <ol>
            <li>Definitions</li>
            <li>Consonant shift rules (tbw)</li>
            <li>Vowel alternation rules</li>
            <li>Consonant gradaton rules</li>
            <li>Rules for cleaning up and composing end result</li>
          </ol>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>The structure of this document</title>
          <p>The next section presents a general discussion on the rule format of xfst. Thereafter, the rule types of the rule file will be dealt with, in the order indicated in the 5-point list given above.</p>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Rule format and the cascade of rules</title>
        <p>Xfst rules are of the following format: interface offers 4 different operator</p>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>The definitions</title>
        <p>There is no section corresponding to the Alphabet section of twolc. The sets are defined as such by means of the operator OR (written &quot;|&quot; ).</p>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>The consonant shift rules</title>
        <p>This section will include a.o. word-final consonant changes</p>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>The vowel alternation rules</title>
      </section>
      <p class="last_modified">Last modified: $Date$, by $Author$</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
